<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter concerning the present state of physick, and the regulation of the practice of it in this kingdom written to a doctor here in London.</title>
            <author>T. M.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1665</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 85 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A70658</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M81C</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32085</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12319513</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12319513</idno>
            <idno type="VID">59448</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A70658)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59448)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books,1641-1700 ; 1016:18 or 1725:54)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter concerning the present state of physick, and the regulation of the practice of it in this kingdom written to a doctor here in London.</title>
                  <author>T. M.</author>
                  <author>Merret, Christopher, 1614-1695.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>65 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Jo. Martyn and Ja. Allestry ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1665.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: T.M.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Christopher Merret by NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. 65.</note>
                  <note>This item appears at reel 1016:18 as Wing M1837 (number cancelled in Wing 2nd ed.), and at reel 1725:54 as Wing M81C.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of originals in the British and Bodleian Libraries.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Medicine --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Physicians --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:59448:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>LETTER Concerning the preſent State OF PHYSICK, And the REGULATION Of the Practice of it in this KINGDOM.</p>
            <p>Written to a Doctor here in <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <bibl>Hipp. de dec. Hab.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Jo. Martyn</hi> and <hi>Ja. Alleſtry,</hi> at the Bell in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard. 1665.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:59448:2"/>
            <p>Imprimatur.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Mar. 30. 1665.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Joh. Hall, <hi>R. P. D.</hi>
Epiſc. Lond. à Sac. Domeſt.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:59448:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>WORTHY SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>NOw I am ſafely arriv'd here, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tir'd from the noiſe and importunity of publick buſineſs, I have a little leaſure to conſider the Civilities I received from you at <hi>London,</hi> and thank you for them: But <hi>my Lady</hi>—is moſt particularly ſenſible of the favour you did her, in ſending her that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent <hi>Syrup</hi> of your own preparation; and as well for the good effects ſhe has found of it, as for your moſt exquiſite manner of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring it, ſhe ceaſes not to commend it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely to her neareſt Relations, and other <hi>Perſons of Quality,</hi> who will very ſhortly, I know, deſire you to take the trouble of making ſome more of it for them. And as <hi>her Ladyſhip</hi> has been wont alwayes to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn the <hi>Syrups, Conſerves,</hi> and other <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines</hi> of the <hi>Apothecaries,</hi> as nauſeous, ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and unhealthy, compar'd with thoſe which her ſelf and other <hi>Ladies</hi> of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey make, without regard of expence or charge, to have them perfectly good; ſo now
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:59448:3"/>
ſhe does it much more, in conſideration of this which you have ſent her.</p>
            <p>Theſe diſcourſes of <hi>her Ladyſhip</hi> put me in minde of what paſt in that excellent com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of <hi>Virtuoſi</hi> at Sir <hi>Thomas</hi>—Houſe, where you and I had lately the honour to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a noble entertainment. And in truth all then preſent did very much reſent the <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy eſtate of the profeſſion of Phyſick, as it now ſtands in this Kingdom,</hi> both in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the worthineſs of the thing it ſelf, and its mighty concernments in humane life, and the ſociety of mankinde; as alſo, as it is an honourable way, wherein all the <hi>Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> of <hi>England</hi> have been ever accuſtomed to breed and educate ſome of their Children. And in both theſe reſpects there is no <hi>Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> in the <hi>Nation,</hi> but ought to take him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf concerned to ſecure it ſo far from the rude pretences of vain and bold men, that in the firſt place it may be really ſerviceable to thoſe ends for which <hi>Heaven</hi> mercifully gave it, and alſo may be a decent and worthy means of <hi>ſubſistence,</hi> as it hath hitherto been, to perſons of <hi>ingenuous Birth</hi> and <hi>liberal Education,</hi> who ſhall in purſuance of thoſe noble ends addreſs themſelves to the Study of it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:59448:3"/>Now becauſe you know very well that my <hi>curioſity</hi> and <hi>inclination</hi> have ever led me to a more then ordinary conſideration of that which you <hi>profeſs,</hi> you will the leſs wonder to finde me <hi>offering ſome propoſitions, which,</hi> in my poor opinion, <hi>will remedy the preſent defects both in the method and practice of it, restore it to its primitive and moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent form, and effectually eſtabliſh it in that degree of honour and eſtimation which all Ages have ſo justly had for it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas I have ſeveral times found both your ſelf and ſome other <hi>Phyſicians</hi> of my acquaintance poſſeſt with apprehenſions, becauſe <hi>our Houſe</hi> did not paſs the Patent, by <hi>His Majesty</hi> lately granted to the <hi>Colledge:</hi> though I will not make my ſelf guilty of ſo much raſhneſs as to cenſure the adviſe by which that affair was governed; yet I verily perſwade my ſelf, if inſtead of that long Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent <hi>De novo,</hi> you had followed the example of your Anceſtors, who finding ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects in the firſt Act of their Incorporation, made in 14. H. 8. Choſe rather to bring into the <hi>Parliament</hi> ſmall <hi>Additional Bills,</hi> praying ſuch new powers as might enable them to put in execution the true intents of the firſt Act,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:59448:4"/>
as that of 38. H. 8. In which they deſire the priviledge of <hi>viſiting the Wares of Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries:</hi> and afterward, <hi>Primo Mariae,</hi> another Bill requiring the <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> to be aſſiſting to them in the execution of this Power, which was forgot before. And likewiſe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other clauſe was deſired, commanding <hi>Goal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> to receive and keep in ſafe cuſtody ſuch <hi>Priſoners</hi> as ſhould from time to time be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by the <hi>Authority</hi> granted to the <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> till they ſhould by them be thereof diſcharged: I ſay, if ſome ſuch courſe as this had been taken, I make no doubt but the zeal and care of this Houſe is ſuch for the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and advancement of all true <hi>Learning in the Nation,</hi> that it would have paſs'd with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out much debate: But conſidering the length of the <hi>new Charter;</hi> the great numbers of men of ſeveral ſorts that made oppoſition, and pretended high exceptions againſt it; the many weighty and important things at that time upon their hands, and ſo the little leaſure they had then to examine a buſineſs of that nature, as they ought to do; It is to me no great wonder that it was for the preſent laid aſide.</p>
            <p>I have great hope, That whatever may be
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:59448:4"/>
               <hi>propos'd</hi> for the effectual advancement of this <hi>noble Art,</hi> that does not onely ſerve the neceſſities of humane Life, but alſo furniſh <hi>Philoſophy</hi> with ſo great a number of real and uſeful <hi>Experiments,</hi> will be ſincerely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded and conſider'd; from the particular <hi>genius</hi> and inclination of the Age wherein we live, which to me ſeems in a peculiar manner directed to the <hi>contemplation of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture:</hi> And although many admirable Spirits flouriſh'd in the former Age, and labour'd in moſt kinde of humane knowledge; yet the honour of the <hi>true method of penetrating into the cauſes of natural things is due onely to ours:</hi> For, excepting the Divine Wit of <hi>Copernicus,</hi> none that I remember of that time did any thing of moment in <hi>natural Philoſophy.</hi> And I look upon <hi>Galileo</hi> as the firſt that introduc'd any ſound and real <hi>ſpecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations</hi> in that way, by firſt diſcerning the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity and uſe of <hi>Geometrical Theories</hi> in the conſiderations of <hi>Nature.</hi> This fortunate beginning was well purſu'd by <hi>Kepler,</hi> and brought to a great degree of perfection by <hi>D. Cartes,</hi> whoſe incomparable Books have kindled in mens mindes ſuch an ardour of ſearching into the cauſes of things, that the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:59448:5"/>
               <hi>great Spirits</hi> of our time ſeem all in a flame; and not onely ſuch perſons as have been bred in Letters, and Study, but men of all <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions</hi> and <hi>Buſineſſes,</hi> even <hi>Princes</hi> themſelves are toucht with this inclination, as the <hi>Prince Leopoldo</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi> but eſpecially <hi>His Moſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Majeſty,</hi> who has ſet on foot the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt <hi>deſign</hi> for this end that ever any Nation ſaw, by Founding his <hi>Royal Society for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of Natural Philoſophy by Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riments,</hi> which will certainly be as Immortal as his own Name and Fortunes.</p>
            <p>If then we conſider how much <hi>the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Phyſick,</hi> well conſtituted and manag'd, will not only adminiſter infinite occaſions to the <hi>ſpeculative</hi> men of this buſie and enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Age; but likewiſe of how much greater importance all its <hi>Experiments</hi> are, both to the publick, and to every one in particular; we need not doubt but <hi>His Majeſty</hi> will believe that <hi>His Colledge of Phyſicians</hi> is worthy of the ſame <hi>Royal Care,</hi> that other <hi>Princes, his Predeceſſors of Famous Memory,</hi> have had for it: And the <hi>Parliament</hi> afford that <hi>Countenance</hi> and <hi>Authority,</hi> which ſhall be requiſite for it <hi>in Affairs of ſo great Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence.</hi> And I eaſily perſwade my ſelf, That
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:59448:5"/>
if that <hi>moſt Learned and Excellent Society of Men</hi> would take ſo much leaſure from their Affairs as to conſider the moſt effectual wayes of advancing all the <hi>Deſiderata</hi> of their <hi>Profeſſion,</hi> and ſupplying the preſent Defects of it; they would not only have <hi>the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of the Government,</hi> but alſo the <hi>Thanks of it,</hi> and of <hi>the whole World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the mean time give me the favour to deal frankly with you about this matter; as one alſo a little tranſported with the ſame paſſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate love of real and uſeful <hi>Philoſophy</hi> which I have noted in others; and beſides, have <hi>a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular kindneſs</hi> for their <hi>moſt deſerving Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Imperfections</hi> then which I note in the preſent Method of <hi>exerciſing Phyſick in this Nations are theſe: It loſes all the noble opportunities it might have for the Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it ſelf, and of the knowledge of Nature in General. It is more expoſed to Errors and Miſtakes, dangerous to the Life of Man; and lastly, it is too great a charge to the People when they ſtand in need of it.</hi> All which I conceive to happen by receding from the <hi>ancient Form</hi> and <hi>Method</hi> of <hi>Practice,</hi> which came early into the world with <hi>Phyſick</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:59448:6"/>
it ſelf, and is in all conſiderations moſt natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral to it, and was indeed the uſe of former times, <hi>till good Learning came to be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown and laid waſt by the furious irruption of the Goths.</hi> In thoſe Ages, that which now ſtands divided between the <hi>Chirurgeon and Apothecary,</hi> was the care of the <hi>Phyſician himſelf,</hi> who did not think it too mean a work <hi>to dreſs Wounds, ſet Bones, travel in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition of Herbs, Stones, Mettals, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound Medicines, with his own hands;</hi> and do innumerable other things neceſſary for <hi>this Profeſſion,</hi> which are now accounted <hi>the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry of inferiour Perſons:</hi> And as the quit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of this noble way was the moſt fatal thing that ever fell upon this <hi>God-like Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion;</hi> ſo doubtleſs the true means of reſtoring it to its firſt <hi>Beauty and Divine uſe,</hi> were <hi>to reſume the courſe of wiſer times,</hi> and <hi>ſettle it again in its ancient Conſtitution.</hi> But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a long courſe of time has ſo confirm'd this unhappy evil, and that out of thoſe Parts of <hi>Phyſick</hi> (for ſuch they really are) which the <hi>Phyſician</hi> has deſpis'd, as below him, are riſen two very <hi>worthy Societies of men</hi> as well in this as in other <hi>Nations,</hi> I look upon it for many reſpects as a thing extreamly
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:59448:6"/>
unreaſonable to undertake ſuch an alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as the reſtoring of that ancient way would neceſſarily introduce: yet I do not deſpair but that an expedient might be thought on, which although it do not arrive to the full perfection of that method, yet it approaches (I think) nearer to it then the preſent way, or any other I have yet heard of; and is likewiſe very facil, ready, and practicable, not over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning the preſent ſtate of things; ſo far from doing injury to the <hi>Chirurgeons</hi> or <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries,</hi> as it ſerves rather to preſerve for ever a true and right underſtanding between them and the <hi>Phyſician,</hi> and to defend them all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the aſſaults and pretenſions of <hi>Mounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banks</hi> and other indirect practiſers of Phyſick, and yet comprehends a great deal of the true way of the Ancients above-mention'd, ſo as it maybe fairly hop'd that it will fully anſwer the greateſt part of thoſe ends we have already ſpoken of, and for which Phyſick has been ſo valu'd in the world; and all this without any great trouble, expence, or difficulty either to the ancient Practitioners of this City and Kingdom, or to ſuch as now enter into this Profeſſion.</p>
            <p>Now the Idea I would repreſent, does par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:59448:7"/>
regard theſe three things: Firſt, to render Phyſick of greater ſervice and uſe towards the advancement of Natural Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy, which is ſo univerſally the deſign of the preſent Age. Secondly, To make it more effectual for the great ends of preſerving life, and the reſtoring of health. Laſtly, That theſe ends may be obtain'd with leſs charge and hazard to the people then heretofore.</p>
            <p>And for what concerns the Philoſophical conſideration of Phyſick, I muſt beg the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of ſuch as you call <hi>Rational Phyſicians,</hi> if I ſo far diſſent from them, as to believe Phyſick (ſuch as it is at preſent) rather to be a maſs of noble Experiments, in which Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy might finde excellent matter to write upon, than a Science perfectly form'd and eſtabliſh'd upon ſound and unqueſtionable verities. For, If we contemplate the common principles explicated in the Phyſiological part of it, we ſhall finde them very barren and unfruitful of ſuch Notions as are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum'd to come from them: and very far from opening a proſpect into thoſe moſt intricate and numberleſs <hi>Phaenomena</hi> which happen in the Body of man, and inſtead of that good which might well be expected from principles
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:59448:7"/>
of true and demonſtrated Reaſon, by which you might have been directed to ſuch a <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodus medendi</hi> as ſhould grow out of the true knowledge of the cauſes of things. Theſe principles have produc'd two great evils. 1. Inſtead of the true way of the <hi>Ancients,</hi> of educating Youth in exerciſes of <hi>Anatomy,</hi> viſiting the Sick with their Maſters, examin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the nature of Simples in Fields and Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, practiſing to compound Medicines with their own hands; they are bred onely to <hi>Diſputation</hi> and the fond Controverſies of Books. And 2dly, They have cauſed the cares of <hi>Anatomy,</hi> inſpection of <hi>Vegetables, Minerals, &amp;c.</hi> (although from theſe ariſe the greateſt part of thoſe <hi>Experiments</hi> which are to be the foundation of a <hi>Medical Philoſophy</hi>) to lie unobſerv'd and neglected in ſuch hands as are no way capable to make a true uſe of them. Therefore for the effective application of the principles of a better Philoſophy to the noble <hi>Experiments</hi> of <hi>Phyſick,</hi> in which vaſt deſign <hi>Des Cartes</hi> hath reſolv'd to ſpend the whole remainder of his life; it will be neceſſary to bring again thoſe <hi>Experiments</hi> into the hands of ſuch perſons who know how to manage and employ them for the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:59448:8"/>
ſervice both of <hi>Philoſophy</hi> and <hi>Phyſick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I look upon your learned <hi>Colledge of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians</hi> as the onely company of men in this Kingdom, who are in a juſt capacity of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing this good deſign; being ſuch men, as (without the vanity of over-admiring our ſelvs) may truly be ſaid to have advanc'd Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick more theſe laſt forty years, then any one Society of Phyſicians in <hi>Europe:</hi> Eſpecially, ſince I hear they have made ſo great an acceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of worthy and ingenious perſons to their number, and that not onely of ſuch as are reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in <hi>London,</hi> but alſo in all other parts of the Kingdom; by which means, a noble correſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pondence may be eſtabliſhed, concerning the Diſeaſes incident to ſeveral parts, as Where they take their riſe, and what their motion and progreſs is, as was of late years obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable <hi>in the Rickets,</hi> &amp;c. The nature of the reſpective Soils, as to <hi>Vegetables, Earths, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals, Metals, &amp;c.</hi> Alterations of Weather and Seaſons, and many other things relating to the Buſineſs of Phyſick. Alſo by this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of their number, you have the aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of ſo many worthy perſons for the carrying on of this excellent deſign.</p>
            <p>I ſhould think it therefore adviſable in the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:59448:8"/>
firſt place, that your Learned Society would divide all their affairs (after the example of the moſt Honourable Aſſembly of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) among ſeveral <hi>Committees</hi> to be aſſign'd for that purpoſe. And although the <hi>Phyſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logical</hi> part, which takes upon it ſelf to expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate the cauſes of all that follows after, be I confeſs in order of Nature the firſt, yet will it be found the laſt in order of Time: as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing indeed the reſult, product, or iſſue of many laborious and careful <hi>Experiments,</hi> which are firſt to be made in the other parts of this Noble Art, before a <hi>Medical Phyſiolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy</hi> can be well and firmly conſtituted.</p>
            <p>Therefore your firſt care will be (in my opinion) to appoint <hi>the Committee for Anato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my's,</hi> which ſhould conſiſt of ſuch a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent number of men, as that the whole buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Anatomy might be diſtributed in eaſie proportions amongſt them all. As for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, to ſome the conſideration of the <hi>Brain</hi> ſhould be aſſign'd, to others of the <hi>Heart,</hi> to others <hi>the Juyces of the Body,</hi> to others the <hi>Bones,</hi> and the like, which you know bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter how to digeſt then I: And theſe to be conſider'd as well in all other <hi>Animals,</hi> as in the body of Man, that ſo by comparing one
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:59448:9"/>
with another, we may come to inveſtigate their true and genuine uſes: <hi>Inſpection</hi> alſo to be made into all <hi>morbid</hi> Bodies that can be procur'd (for which reaſon all or any Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of this Committee to have free acceſs to the ſeveral <hi>Hoſpitals</hi>) to finde out the <hi>Anoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly's</hi> which Diſeaſes introduce: Likewiſe theſe conſiderations ſhould be in part <hi>Geome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trical,</hi> noting the juſt figure, weight, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion (as near as can be) of every thing, and that not only of its whole bulk or mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt cavities, but by the advantage of the <hi>Microſcope,</hi> as far as may be diſcerned, of its more minute parts, their frame, and texture. Partly alſo <hi>Phyſical,</hi> according to all their ſenſible qualities, partly <hi>Chymical,</hi> by the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalyſis</hi> of the fire, or any convenient <hi>Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruum.</hi> Nor would this create much trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to any man, being divided into ſo many hands; and yet the general deſign would ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance more in a few years this way, then it could by the ſingle induſtry of particular men in a whole age. For neither this nor the other <hi>Committees</hi> ſhould be requir'd to bring in an account of their proceedings above once in a year, nor to meet together above once a moneth, unleſs they or any number of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:59448:9"/>
them ſhould be willing to meet oftner to diſcourſe of their affairs, and ſuggeſt <hi>Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riments</hi> to one another.</p>
            <p>After this manner, <hi>another Committee</hi> ſhould be inſtituted <hi>for the Hiſtory of Diſeaſes.</hi> (For what I deſign to propoſe concerns onely <hi>matter of Fact,</hi> and the true ſtating of <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments</hi> in order to the building a Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy upon them.) By <hi>the Hiſtory of Diſeaſes</hi> I mean a perfect and exact <hi>Narrative</hi> of thoſe Signes which you call <hi>Diagnoſtick and Prog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſtick, together with the experienced method of Curation:</hi> And I think a work of this nature well perform'd would be one of the moſt uſeful things to a Phyſician in the whole world; and I note it as one of the great <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderata</hi> in this Art: all which ſhould be done as well out of all the beſt Authors, as from their own <hi>Practice</hi> and <hi>Obſervation.</hi> For as to Medicaments, by which the effect is done, that which ought to be eſteemed <hi>matter of Fact</hi> is ſo obſcure, and the <hi>Experiment</hi> ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain, that unleſs they can meet with ſome effectual operations of Simples (which will require both good Learning and Judgement to obſervewell) as yet this part will afford lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle matter for the conſideration of a judicious man.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:59448:10"/>Then the whole <hi>Materia Medica,</hi> both ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and compound, ſhould be referr'd to the examination of another <hi>Committee;</hi> every member whereof ſhould have one, two, or more <hi>Simples</hi> or <hi>Compounds</hi> (either <hi>Mineral, Animal,</hi> or <hi>Vegetable</hi>) the nature and vertues of which they ſhould labour by all means poſſible to finde out, as by <hi>colour, taſte, ſcent, infuſion, decoction, deſtillation</hi> before and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Fermentation,</hi> and all other poſſible wayes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Endeavouring in this manner to finde out what things are moſt operative with or without any exquiſite and elaborate prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, by which Chymiſts do often rather deſtroy then heighten the vertues of the Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: Alſo for compounds to enquire the true method of mixing things together, that ſome may not annihilate the force of others, and ſo altogether become ineffectual, which will produce an incredible alteration in moſt of the <hi>Pharmacopaea</hi>'s now in uſe, bring in the true and ancient way of medication by Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and ſo furniſh us with real <hi>Experiments</hi> both of uſe to humane life, and alſo to the advancement of Philoſophy, being without doubt the moſt eaſie and effectual way (by dividing a work ſo vaſt amongſt ſo many) to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:59448:10"/>
form and build up ſuch a <hi>natural Hiſtory both of Galenical and Chymical Medicines</hi> as has been long deſired, but never yet ſeen in the world. And this were a more likely and hopeful way, then to put the buſineſs of <hi>Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſtry</hi> (which as I hear ſome do ſo importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately labour for) into the hands of a few men (for the moſt part) unlearned, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provided of ſuch principles and helps as ſhould make them able to reaſon and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude intelligibly from that <hi>brave ſtock of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments</hi> which this Art affords: And for this cauſe onely it has been (until of late) ſo unſerviceable to Philoſophy, and produc'd nothing but idle and extravagant Theories, ſuch as thoſe of <hi>Paracelſus</hi> and <hi>Helmont;</hi> who, if they had been as good <hi>Philoſophers</hi> as they were <hi>Operators,</hi> would have done a great deal more ſervice to mankinde.</p>
            <p>Laſtly for <hi>Medicaments</hi> themſelves, and the application of them to the cure of Diſeaſes, which is the principal thing the generality of mankinde expects from Phyſick; I take that not to be the buſineſs of any one or more <hi>Committees,</hi> but of their whole number uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in one common conſent; and I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded it were no difficult thing to take ſuch
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:59448:11"/>
a courſe here, as might ſecure your Practice entirely to your ſelves, and hinder others, who now are ſuſpected (how juſtly I do not ſay) to go about to uſurp it; take away <hi>the exceſſive charge of Phyſick,</hi> which renders it very burdenſome to the people, and leſs pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to your ſelves; and laſtly, make it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come more effectual and powerful for the curing of Diſeaſes, and preſerving the health and life of Man.</p>
            <p>And all this ſeems to me to conſiſt in the execution of one facil and eaſie thing, That is to ſay, <hi>That the Colledge of Phyſicians would pleaſe to enact, under a ſevere Penalty, That from henceforth none of their Members ſhould make uſe of the common and more modern way of ſending Bills to Apothecaries Shops; but inſtead of that, To buy their Phyſick of the ſaid Apothecaries more or leſs, as their practice ſhall requi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e. Together with expreſs order, That no Phyſick ſhould be given to any Patient without ſetting it first down in ſuch manner and form as was accuſtomed before in the Bills ſent to A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothecaries, with the Patients name, Year of our Lord, and day of the Moneth; and every ſuch Bill to be fil'd up and kept by the Phyſician. And the Phyſick ſo bought to be diſpenſed at
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:59448:11"/>
home to the Patient by the Phyſician himſelf, or his Servant, (or ſome young Student, educated under him for that and all other things apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to his Art) at reaſonable rates: The Phyſician not to demand or expect any other pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment but for his Phyſick only, unleſs he be ſent for out of his own Houſe, and then to be paid his accuſtomed Fee, according to the Ability of the Patient. Yet this not to prejudice any other Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician of the Colledge, who would take on him the Trouble and Charge of preparing all his Phyſick himſelf, which was the uſe of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The reaſons of this Propoſition, and the <hi>advantages</hi> it brings are very many, and of great conſideration. 1. It appoaches as near to the genuine and true Method of <hi>Hippocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, Galen,</hi> and other great Maſters of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, as the preſent conſtitution of things will admit. And though your Self very well know what they did this way, yet give me leave to put you in minde of ſome paſſages of <hi>Hippocrates</hi> and <hi>Galen</hi> to this effect; for which I was lately beholding to Dr.—our worthy friend; He firſt acquainted me with the Letter of <hi>Hippocrates</hi> to an Herbariſt his acquaintance, to provide him things for the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:59448:12"/>
Cure of <hi>Democritus,</hi> where he demands only Simples, as Juyces and Tears of Plants, which he orders to be ſent in Glaſs Veſſels, and Leavs, Roots, and Flowers, which he bids him put up in earthen Pots well clos'd; he directs him to the time of gathering them, and the place, which was not difficult for him to do who was ſo well knowing of their Natures, ſince he tells us how often he viſited his Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, and contemplated with wonder that <hi>Myſterious place the Earth,</hi> which brings forth<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Animals, Plants, Food, Medicine, and Riches. And theſe Simples ſo bought and received were by himſelf to be prepared and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, as occaſion ſhould require. I need not deſcribe to you the Phyſicians Shop out of the ſame Author, who has a whole Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of it; I ſhall content my ſelf with a paſſage out of his Book, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation and manners of a Phyſician,</hi> which evidently ſhows, how that Phyſicians of that time, did not onely <hi>diſpenſe</hi> their own <hi>Medicines</hi> themſelves, but make them too in <hi>Shops</hi> of their own, by <hi>Hippocrates</hi> called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. His words are theſe, <hi>A Phycſiian,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>ought to have his Shop or</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>provided with plenty of all neceſſary things, as Lint,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:59448:12"/>
Rowlers, Splints; all ſorts of Chirurgical In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments; alſo of Medicines, as for Wounds, for the Eyes, &amp;c. alwayes ready prepar'd. Let there be likewiſe</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>in readineſs at all times another ſmall Cabinet (as it were) of ſuch things, as may ſerve for occaſions of going far from home; have alſo ready all ſorts of Plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, Potions, purging Medicines, ſo contriv'd that they may keep ſome conſiderable time; and likewiſe ſuch as may be had and uſed while they are freſh. The advantage of this will be very great; for when you come to a Patient you will be more ready and certain what to do, having all things prepar'd by you for your occaſions.</hi> Which is indeed a moſt excellent reaſon to perſwade this courſe, and much better then the haſty and praecipitate way of writing Bills.</p>
            <p>And for <hi>Galen,</hi> the ſame worthy Perſon has inform'd me, There are ſo many things in him to this effect, that it would be too great a vanity for me to tell you how he travell'd to <hi>Cyprus</hi> to enquire the nature of Mettals, ſee <hi>Pompholyx, Cadmia, Diphryges, Vitriol;</hi> and brought home ſuch quantity with him as might ſerve him all his life; how he viſited <hi>Paleſtine</hi> for its rich <hi>Balſom,</hi> and the <hi>Bitumen</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:59448:13"/>
found there; or how curious he was at <hi>Lemnos,</hi> to ſee the <hi>Terra Lemnia</hi> there: he went like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to <hi>Crete, Alexandria,</hi> and ſeveral other places for the ſame end, and moſt earneſtly conjures all who deſign'd themſelves to this Study to do as he did, and provide againſt the frauds and abuſes of Impoſtors; not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the great expence neceſſary for ſuch an undertaking. And a little after com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains of a ſort of men, who contented themſelves to know Simples out of Books, Becauſe (ſayes he) the knowledge of ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble things can never be acquir'd but by fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent inſpection, and often repeated views. I need not adde that he had a <hi>Repoſitory,</hi> which he call'd his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (from whence the name of <hi>Apothecary</hi> came) where he tells us his Medicines were alwayes under his Eye, or in his hand. To acquaint you that he made the Emperours Treacle with his own hands, or dreſs'd the wounded <hi>Gladiators</hi> himſelf; nor ever gave any Medicine of which he had not firſt taſted and ſmelt, nay, made experiment of it (he ſayes) upon his own perſon, and how he was hated by the Roman Phyſicians for uſing Simples and plain Medicines; would from me to you be extreamly impertinent, who know
<pb facs="tcp:59448:13"/>
all this ſo much better then I. I ſhall content my ſelf for the preſent to rectifie a miſtake of ſome who think that there was a trade of men in <hi>Galens</hi> time, ſuch as our <hi>Apothecaries</hi> now are: but this proceeds from want of underſtanding the ancient ſenſe of the word <hi>Pharmacopola,</hi> which in thoſe times ſignifi'd not an <hi>Apothecary,</hi> but ſuch a perſon as we now call a <hi>Mountebank;</hi> one who ſold Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick in Markets, Fairs, and other places of publick Concourſe: And theſe were ever re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted at <hi>Rome</hi> among the baſeſt and meaneſt men of the Town, and were obnoxious to the common Laws made againſt Rogues and Vagabonds, as <hi>Pliny</hi> has noted; And if there were nothing elſe we might take their Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter from <hi>Horace.</hi>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>Ambubaiarum Collegia, <hi>Pharmacopolae,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Mendici, Mimi, Balatrones, hoc genus omne</l>
               <l>Moeſtum ac ſollicitum eſt Cantoris morte <hi>Tigelli.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>And out of <hi>Max. Tyrius, We ſhall find</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>that there is no kinde of good thing but ſome evil will endeavour to counterfeit it;</hi> ſo a <hi>Sycophant</hi> will imitate an <hi>Orator,</hi> a <hi>Sophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> a <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> And a
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:59448:14"/>
               <hi>Quack</hi> will pretend himſelf a <hi>Phyſician.</hi> And for the Word <hi>Apothecary</hi> in Scripture, 'tis ſo well known, <hi>that word</hi> means only <hi>ſellers of rich Oyntments, Perfumes, Balſoms,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and ſuch other <hi>Coſmeticks</hi> as were in uſe in thoſe Countreys (which ſort of men were after by the <hi>Greeks</hi> call'd <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and among the <hi>Romans</hi> from the place they inhabited <hi>Seplaſiarii, &amp; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nguentarii:</hi>) that I ſhall not give you any further trouble about it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond reaſon for this <hi>Method</hi> is this: The <hi>Phyſician</hi> is hereby oblig'd to make himſelf throughly acquainted with the Nature, Goodneſs, and exact Preparations of Medicines now ſold by the <hi>Apothecary,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Simple or Compound. Otherwiſe he will not know how to lay out his money, and may eaſily be impos'd upon by the diſhoneſty of another, <hi>to the ruine of his Patient, of his Reputation,</hi> and conſequently <hi>of his Livelihood and Subſiſtence.</hi> For what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver accident may happen from the ill prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the <hi>Phyſick,</hi> it will now become the fault of the <hi>Phyſician,</hi> whoſe ignorance, or neglect it was, that he did not provide what was good for his occaſion.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:59448:14"/>
            <p n="3">3. For the reaſon before alledg'd, The Phyſician will be alſo engag'd to frequent viſits of the Apothecaries Shop, to view his Simples, and conſider his manner of prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; from which he will likewiſe gain many opportunities of <hi>Improving Medicines</hi> already in uſe, both as to their <hi>Eſſicacy</hi> and <hi>Operation,</hi> and alſo as to their <hi>Taſte</hi> and <hi>Scent,</hi> which ought to be one great part of a Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians care, and is now too much neglected; although nothing can be more his intereſt then this. He will be alſo more able to <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent new Medicines,</hi> and bring in the uſe of Simples yet <hi>undiſcover'd:</hi> Laſtly he will have frequent occaſions of obſerving many excellent <hi>Phaenomena,</hi> which now paſs unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded through the hands of Apothecaries and their Servants, for the uſe and ſervice of <hi>Philoſophy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. This renders the Phyſician much more acceptable to every Patient, and affords him many real opportunities of gaining his hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty kindeneſs and affection, which others now enjoy: and alſo takes away the Scandal and Reflexion which is caſt upon the Phyſician by ſome <hi>Apothecaries,</hi> and upon both the <hi>Phyſician</hi> and <hi>Apothecary</hi> by <hi>Mountebanks,</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:59448:15"/>
and thoſe that call themſelves <hi>Chymiſts.</hi> For the firſt, Although the writing of a Bill and directing proper Remedies for every Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per be the reſult of the pains, and careful Study of many Years, and the Phyſician that preſcribes well may juſtly be ſaid (under God Almighty) to be principal in the cure of the Diſeaſe; yet an ordinary Patient is not ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of this, but thinks it very hard to part with ten ſhillings for a few words in Paper; eſpecially when he muſt go from thence to the Apothecary, and there be at another ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary charge for what was preſcribed, and alſo uſe ſome means beſide, to oblige the Apothecary to prepare it well: Whereas if the ſame Phyſician ſhould, inſtead of that, give the Phyſick it ſelf that is to be taken, at a reaſonable and moderate price, aſſuring the Patient of his care to prepare it as it ought to be, and alſo his counſel and advice for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing (unleſs ſent for out of his own houſe) he muſt needs infinitely gain the heart and good will of every man. Beſides many oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions would be offer'd of giving to the Poor for nothing, which is Chriſtian Charity; and ſometimes alſo to the Rich themſelves, of which a wiſe man will know how to make
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:59448:15"/>
an honourable and diſcreet advantage, and put frequent obligations upon them. For the ſecond, I remember well the Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries counſel laid a great and unhandſome ſcandal upon all your Colledge, and that in publick, before a Committee of our Houſe, affirming you incompetent to viſit their Shops, or to make a judgement of their Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines; and though it was then ſaid with much raſhneſs and paſſion (there being ſo great a number of your Learned Members excellently knowing this way) yet I wiſh there had been no cauſe to think it in ſome part true. But this will for ever prevent all ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumny of that nature; for now you will un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand them better then the Apothecaries themſelves. On the other ſide, the <hi>Mounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banks, Chymists, &amp;c.</hi> have nothing to boaſt of ſo much, as <hi>the making their own Phyſick,</hi> recommending their great induſtry and care to finde out and prepare exactly the beſt of Medicines: and accuſing the Shops of dull, enactive, and ſlight preparations, and your ſelves of too much delicacy, pride, ſloth, and ignorance, for not providing better, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king pains (as they pretend to do) in ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the <hi>Rich and large Stock of Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:59448:16"/>
which the wiſdom and bounty of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture has created in ſo great plenty for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of men.</p>
            <p n="5">5. This will reſtore the ancient, true, and only fit way of <hi>breeding up young Students</hi> in this Faculty: That is to ſay, in exerciſes of <hi>Anatomy,</hi> knowledge of <hi>Herbs,</hi> mixing and compounding <hi>Medicines,</hi> viſiting the Sick un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>direction</hi> of a grave <hi>Phyſician;</hi> not as they are now for the moſt part, in <hi>ſpecula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> diſcourſes only, and reading of Books. Thus was the late famous Dr. <hi>Wright</hi> the younger educated under Dr. <hi>Fox,</hi> and was the firſt Phyſician that diſſected at the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, which till his time had ever made uſe of <hi>Chirurgeons</hi> in their <hi>publick Theatre.</hi> And while the young Phyſician employes his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry in ſuch ſervices as theſe for the elder, he gains, (beſides what is learn't from Books and Authors) the long experience of the other, <hi>ſees his Patients, hears him diſcourſe of their ſeveral caſes, conſiders the Medicines pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for them, and obſerves their ſeveral ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects:</hi> All which advantages you now in vain give away to <hi>Apothecaries,</hi> to whom the <hi>Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of Phyſick</hi> does not belong. And if this has been the courſe that all mankinde has
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:59448:16"/>
ever taken to raiſe and propagate <hi>Practical</hi> Arts and Trades of daily uſe in humane life, why ſhould it not be us'd in Phyſick, which is a <hi>Practical Art</hi> of ſo much greater conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence? eſpecially if we conſider how dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous the errors of this Profeſſion are, and how neceſſary a <hi>Practical Education</hi> is for any man that intends the exerciſe of it, as <hi>Galen,</hi> and more particularly <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> often inculcates, and the nature of the thing makes it evident. I need not tell you how it was confin'd till the time of <hi>Hippocrates</hi> to one ſingle Family, under a curſe not to communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate it to any <hi>other,</hi> nor reckon up the many famous men who were <hi>Galen</hi>'s Maſters, from whom he learn't this Art, and whom he men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions with ſo much honour. Yet give me the favour to recall an excellent Paſſage of <hi>Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrates</hi> to this effect. He adviſes a Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an when he carries his Diſciples with him to<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> a Patient, <hi>to appoint in his abſence ſuch a one of them to obſerve the Patient as is well advanc'd and ſtudied in this Art, and knows what is fit to be done, and how to give him an account of the caſe, that ſo he may be ignorant of nothing that is material, though he could not be there himſelf.</hi> Theſe things conſider'd, if a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:59448:17"/>
of three or four years ſtanding in either of our <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities</hi> (for none elſe ſhould be entertained by any) ſhould agree with a Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician for a reaſonable conſideration and acknowledgement to be made (which was held very honourable in <hi>Hippocrates</hi> age, as appears in his Oath, and was the practice at that time) to live with him till he be <hi>Doctor in that Faculty</hi> (being oblig'd to take his <hi>Degrees</hi> in due time with performance of all the accuſtomed <hi>Exerciſes:</hi> nor to be admitted to them without the <hi>Certificate</hi> of the ſaid Phyſician, both concerning his <hi>Time</hi> and good <hi>Deportment.</hi>) Or if a perſon already <hi>Batchelor in Phyſick</hi> ſhould contract to ſtay till he become <hi>Doctor,</hi> taking his <hi>Degrees,</hi> as was before expreſt: and theſe two abſolutely prohibited <hi>Practice</hi> till they have taken the degree of <hi>Doctor:</hi> Or if any already <hi>Doctor</hi> ſhould contract for as long a time as he and an elder Phyſician can agree (not to <hi>Practiſe</hi> during his continuance with him, without his knowledge and conſent) <hi>I</hi> ſhould think for the reaſons alledg'd, it were the beſt and moſt deſireable way to inſtitute men for that Profeſſion, and might with great faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity be brought into practice, and is at this
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:59448:17"/>
time the uſe of many parts of <hi>Italy.</hi> Nor does a Phyſician run half the fortune of other men who breed up Youth to their Trades, ſince the old Phyſician will ever be held by the world for the more able man. Nor let any man think to diſgrace this Method as Mecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical, by the imputation of taking Apprenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; ſince the word Apprentice is entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the honourable Profeſſion of the Law, whoſe younger Students have been call'd Apprentices to the Law; but however this be, it were very fond for ſo poor an occaſion, to neglect a thing that is founded upon the evidence of true reaſon it ſelf. Nor indeed ſhould they be received in the capacity of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, or under that name, but rather of young <hi>Students, Friends,</hi> or <hi>vertuous Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions</hi> to be inſtructed in this worthy Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; the drudgery of all things reſting whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon ſome ordinary Servant kept by eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one for the uſes of his Family: and I make no doubt but there are very many inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious young men in <hi>England,</hi> who would be very glad, and take it for a great honour, to be thus received by ſome of the Grandees, and great Practitioners; and their Friends believe whatever is beſtowed on them in this
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:59448:18"/>
way very well and honourably employed.</p>
            <p n="6">6. This will bring all ſorts of men both rich and poor to apply themſelves immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Phyſician, and ſo in a ſhort time quite overthrow the practice of <hi>Mountebanks,</hi> and other <hi>Perſons</hi> ignorant of the Art of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, who now take upon them to adminiſter it, contrary to the <hi>Laws of the Nation,</hi> and to the great <hi>prejudice</hi> and <hi>damage</hi> of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: For it is not to be thought, but all men who have occaſion to uſe Phyſick would much more willingly addreſs themſelves to a ſober and intelligent Phyſician, then to this ſort of men: But firſt, the <hi>charge of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice is great,</hi> and then as great the <hi>charge of Phyſick,</hi> at the <hi>Apothecaries;</hi> which things ſo affright the ordinary ſort of people, that they very unwillingly come to a Phyſician, and many periſh for want of due help. And I am perſwaded if there were no other reaſon then this, every Phyſician who is touch'd with Conſcience, Honour, or Philoſophy, will be very glad to entertain ſome <hi>expedient,</hi> that may remove the <hi>ſcandalous Reluctancy</hi> that moſt people have of uſing this Profeſſion.</p>
            <p n="7">7. This will render the practice of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick more ſucceſsful, plentiful, and of no leſs
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:59448:18"/>
advantage then before: As for the ſucceſs; beſides that the Phyſician may juſtly have a greater confidence in his Phyſick, now he takes care himſelf to have nothing but what is good, than he could before when it was made up out of his ſight; he has alſo the opportunity of ſeeing every Diſeaſe in its <hi>firſt riſe,</hi> and <hi>beginning,</hi> which gives him a mighty advantage for the true underſtanding and cure of it. And for the encreaſe of his Practice the bringing ſo many people of all ſorts to him for advice, who before durſt not come, will much enlarge his <hi>Buſineſs</hi> and <hi>Experience,</hi> and not make his <hi>Profit</hi> leſs: for though he gain nothing more, by the Phyſick he gives, than what will barely recompence the trouble of himſelf and his <hi>Miniſter</hi> for diſpenſing it; yet he will not loſe, ſince in all <hi>acute caſes,</hi> and ſuch as hinder the Patients <hi>attendance in perſon,</hi> (and he is ſeldom ſent for in any other) he muſt neceſſarily be brought home, as he now is to all people of condition.</p>
            <p n="8">8. The trouble of undertaking is but lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, eſpecially after the firſt entrance into it, and valu'd with the great good it will bring to ſo noble a Faculty; and the great caſe,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:59448:19"/>
profit, and advantage it affords to an Elder Phyſician, not unworthy of conſideration. Firſt the ancient Phyſician may employ the eye, hand, and youthful vigour of the younger to aſliſt the frailties of Age, and humanity. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo it will take off much of the labour of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſits in his own perſon, or when call'd up un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonably at Nights, or when he goes into the Countrey to other Patients, or to refreſh himſelf a little from the toils of Buſineſs: For the people would finde greater ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the viſits of another Phyſician bred un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him they ſo much confide in, than when he is forc'd to ſend his Apothecary. On the other ſide the Phyſician himſelf would be much better ſatisfied in the report of his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients caſe, as <hi>Hippocrates</hi> has excellently noted.</p>
            <p n="9">9. In ſome reſpects, this way is much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then that uſed by the Ancients of making all their Phyſick at home. 1. It is leſs <hi>trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome;</hi> publick Shops being now open, fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd with all ſorts of Medicines commonly us'd, or where all ſuch Phyſick may be ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly and dextrouſly prepar'd which any man ſhall in particular deſire for his own occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. 2. 'Tis leſs expenſive, for now every
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:59448:19"/>
man buyes only ſo much as he ſhall have uſe for, be it more or leſs; ſo that the charge of money thus laid out is exactly <hi>meaſur'd</hi> to the <hi>proportion</hi> of every ones practice: ſuch as are but juſt entred into buſineſs, will accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly expend but a ſmall matter in Phyſick, and that too may eaſily be diſpens'd by themſelves, with the aſſiſtance of an ordinary domeſtick ſervant, remitting a great many things, as, <hi>common Clyſters, &amp;c.</hi> to the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents own making, giving him only the ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dients, as is now the uſe of the Phyſicians in <hi>Paris.</hi> 3. 'Tis more certain: for a man that provides his own Phyſick, and makes it him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, will never know well how to eſtimate his <hi>quantities;</hi> he will have ſometimes too much which turns to loſs; or too little, and ſo want when he has occaſion to make uſe of it; but now he buyes only what is neceſſary, and can never want, unleſs you ſuppoſe all the Shops in Town <hi>exhauſted;</hi> for there will be nothing in common uſe, but one or other Shop will afford it: to which we may adde, that he has now his choice of what is both cheapeſt and beſt, whereas the negligence of a Servant might either make a thing ill, or in the making ſpoil it ſo, that he might begin a
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:59448:20"/>
new, though preſent occaſion may require it for uſe. 4. It will enlarge the <hi>materia Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca,</hi> and make a greater <hi>variety of Practice,</hi> which muſt needs be of excellent concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, unleſs we think (as ſome over-bold men have lately don) that nature has made ſo <hi>ample proviſions</hi> in vain: but they who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide at home, will be lead (to ſave expenſe as much as they can) to confine themſelves to a very ſcanty and narrow method of Practice: as ſome fooliſh perſons know no other Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caments but what are made from <hi>Mercury</hi> and <hi>Antimony,</hi> deſpiſing all the <hi>royal Appara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus of Gods Creatures</hi> beſide; though we cannot doubt but the vaſt alterations, and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious diſpoſitions of Bodies, Climates, Diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes were particularly aim'd at by Nature in her ſo infinite and magnificent proviſions of help. And though I do not deny that Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicaments, <hi>Antimonials,</hi> and <hi>Mercurials</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cently prepar'd are of wonderful efficacy; yet it is ſo well known they cannot perform half that is ſo idly promis'd by their admirers at all times, and in all bodies; and that a mean and ordinary <hi>decoction</hi> has in ſome caſes effected what they could not do. 5. By preſerving the publick ſellers of Medicines
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:59448:20"/>
or <hi>Pharmacopolae,</hi> you comply with the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent State of things which cannot well admit any other change then what has been ſaid.</p>
            <p n="10">10. And whereas many apprehenſions, and ſuſpicions have lately ariſen between the <hi>Phyſician</hi> and <hi>Apothecary,</hi> as if the Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry did invade the Phyſicians practice: This way will for ever moſt entirely and abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſecure his <hi>Practice</hi> and <hi>Profeſſion</hi> to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. For now the Apothecary will never ſee a Phyſicians Bill (from which they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes take direction) nor the Patient himſelf, and ſo be utterly ignorant of that caſe for which the Phyſick is prepar'd and us'd; nor will he hear the Phyſician reaſon and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of the due times and manner of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtring it, or explain the nature and cauſe of the diſtemper, nor have occaſions of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficious intervening between the Phyſician and Patient, nor diſpenſe the Phyſick with praiſe of his own great pains and care in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring it, as he was wont to do: ſo that he will quickly free himſelf of the imputation ſome now lay upon him, and be for ever un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to do the Phyſician that injury which is now ſuppos'd to be done by ſome of them. <hi>All this the Phyſician obtains by only concealing
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:59448:21"/>
his Bills (the writing of a Bill being, as I may ſay, the myſtery of his Trade) in which therefore he does nothing but what is held moſt reaſonable among all men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">11. This will likewiſe <hi>ſecure the Phyſician another way againſt the ſuppos'd uſurpation of Apothecaries: for if any Apothecary</hi> ſhall take on him <hi>to practiſe Phyſick,</hi> upon notice giv'n <hi>to the Colledge,</hi> it may be <hi>enacted among your ſelves</hi> (without troubling <hi>the Parliament</hi> for new power, and without the envious way of ſining and impriſonment) <hi>That no Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian ſhall buy any Medicines of ſuch Apothecary till the Colledge be fully ſatisfied that he is ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of the injury done to them, and will ceaſe to do the like for the Future.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12. It gives every <hi>Phyſician</hi> as many, or more opportunities of doing kindneſs to his particular friends that are <hi>Apothecaries:</hi> And that is, by being himſelf, and engaging as many <hi>Phyſicians</hi> as he has intereſt in, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come their cuſtomers.</p>
            <p n="13">13. As to matter <hi>of Conſultation</hi> among <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> it is here ſufficiently provided for by <hi>fileing up Bills</hi> of all the <hi>Phyſick</hi> they give; and therefore this is to be required of every man by <hi>the Colledge,</hi> under ſevere <hi>Penalties.</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:59448:21"/>
And if any man have particular Medicines of his own which you call <hi>Noſtra,</hi> the caſe is here the ſame as in the former way. For I am inform'd, every <hi>Phyſician</hi> is oblig'd to <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint the Colledge</hi> with them if it be requir'd. Beſides, this filing of <hi>Bills</hi> (or entring them into a Book) may have another excellent uſe: For doing it <hi>Alphabetically,</hi> a <hi>Phyſician</hi> may by ſome private note diſcern a great while af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which of his Medicines had a good effect, and which had not, or fail'd, and in what <hi>Tempers of Body,</hi> and how to accommodate himſelf to the ſame perſons at other times: and laſtly, may from hence (if he pleaſes) produce great numbers of obſervations, which may well deſerve the <hi>Publick,</hi> and be highly uſeful to Poſterity. And it would be very much for the good <hi>of their Profeſſion, If no Phyſician would for the future write any thing in the practice of Phyſick but what had been experimented by himſelf, and that all the practitioners of it would be more careful to ſet down ſuch remarkable accidents that come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their obſervation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="14">14. This way by making the <hi>Phyſician</hi> a perfect Maſter of the <hi>Materia Medica,</hi> has theſe three great effects, beſides what has
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:59448:22"/>
been mention'd already. 1. It renders him more able to diſcover the uſe of <hi>Simples, when he has occaſion to travel into Forreign Parts,</hi> ſo enlarging both <hi>Phyſick</hi> and <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy</hi> with new and uſeful diſcoveries. 2. He will be more fit to ſerve the Prince in His <hi>Navy</hi> or <hi>Army;</hi> where, if his ſtock of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines be all ſpent or corrupted, without this knowledge he is utterly uncapable of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding himſelf a new, to his own diſhonour, and <hi>prejudice</hi> of others. 3. By obſerving <hi>the ſeveral mutations</hi> that happen in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations of things as well Simple as Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound he will be aſſiſted to conſider <hi>what ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects like them</hi> may happen upon their mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture with the Blood, and other juyces of the Body, and to give a huge light to the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons <hi>of the Phaenomena</hi> both in Health and Sickneſs. Of this that very worthy perſon Dr. <hi>Willis</hi> has already given the world an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent taſte, and promis'd an entire Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe upon that ſubject, which would be of vaſt uſe, and in which he ſtands indebted to the publick.</p>
            <p n="15">15. It is a generous and worthy thing, that <hi>Phyſicians</hi> ſhould be knowing in the <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teria Medica,</hi> as was <hi>Hippocrates, Galen,</hi> and all
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:59448:22"/>
the old <hi>Maſters of this Science.</hi> It has been already ſaid how great the endeavour of theſe brave men was, to acquire a perfect under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of all they made uſe of. And with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt it is a thing moſt indecent and <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural</hi> for a <hi>Phyſician</hi> to deſpiſe the <hi>knowledg of that</hi> by which all his great works are to be effected. <hi>In the old and heroical times of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick,</hi> Medicines were excellently call'd <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>The hands of the gods:</hi> And I think it is the higheſt ſort of ſhame to ſee a <hi>Phyſician</hi> at a loſs for <hi>Medicaments in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey,</hi> where <hi>Nature,</hi> the bountiful <hi>provider of them</hi> has ſo rich and large a Shop open, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he wants his <hi>Apothecary</hi> to write to, or <hi>the knowledge of the things themſelves,</hi> or <hi>the way how to make uſe of them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="16">16. This way has in many great reſpects the advantage of the common courſe of wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Bills to the <hi>Apothecaries.</hi> For in the firſt place, by ſeeing the very things they admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred, by mixing, ordering, compounding them as they have occaſion, by conſideration of the <hi>taſtes, ſcents, and colours</hi> of <hi>Medicines,</hi> and how variouſly all theſe are changed and altered by the mixture of ſeveral things to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, they will be much more able to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:59448:23"/>
in memory what is proper and uſeful for every Diſtemper, then by reading their names in Books onely, <hi>and ſo direct better,</hi> and with greater eaſe, and certainty. Likewiſe by underſtanding <hi>the true wayes of mixture,</hi> and being acquainted with the <hi>taſtes</hi> and <hi>ſcents</hi> of things, a great many errors will be avoided, <hi>and Phyſick be render'd much more pleaſant and palateable:</hi> Finally, a great many <hi>excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Experiments</hi> will be drawn from it, for the uſe of <hi>Philoſophical ſpeculations.</hi> Now in the preſent <hi>Method</hi> of your <hi>Bills,</hi> either the <hi>Phyſician</hi> depends wholly upon the memory of what he has read in Books (which <hi>Galen</hi> greatly condemns) and then we ſhall never hope to promote <hi>this Art</hi> beyond its preſent limits, although 'tis well known there are ſo great treaſures of powerful and active <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines</hi> yet <hi>undiſcovered:</hi> Beſides, if we do not exactly remember the very proportions and meaſures of every thing in every Medicine (which is impoſſible) we cannot reaſonably hope well from it, becauſe (as my Lord <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con</hi> obſerves) the Experiment was made in ſuch quantities only, which when we alter, conſidering the nature of things <hi>à priori,</hi> are altogether unknown to us, we know not what
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:59448:23"/>
we do. And though <hi>Phyſicians</hi> commonly endeavour to provide themſelves rather of the general <hi>materia medica</hi> then of <hi>particular Receipts,</hi> yet if we duely weigh the ſtrange alterations that happen <hi>upon the blending</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral things together, and the unexpected reſults of quite different qualities, the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing ſcent and taſte they acquire many times, eſpecially if their proportions are not preciſely juſt, we ſhall not think it ſtrange, that ſo wiſe a man as that <hi>great Perſon was,</hi> blam'd this laſt and uncertain way. And as to the common <hi>proportions</hi> and <hi>quantities</hi> by which <hi>Phyſicians</hi> govern themſelves in the uſual forms of <hi>Medicines,</hi> they vary ſo much, according to the ſeveral natures of things, that whoever is not well acquainted with the things themſelves ſhall never be able (as <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len</hi> notes) to direct as he ought to do. And none will doubt but any <hi>Phyſician</hi> could make a better <hi>Apozem, Potion, Julep,</hi> or the like, by meaſuring the <hi>Proportions</hi> of each ingredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent by his <hi>taſte</hi> and <hi>ſcent,</hi> then by writing a Bill from the <hi>unexact proportions of Authors,</hi> eſpecially if he be not very well acquainted with the things he preſcribes. In a word, neither theſe proportions themſelves, nor
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:59448:24"/>
their Books had ever been at all, if <hi>Phyſicians</hi> had not in former times been knowing in all Simples, examined their vertues and tempers, enquir'd into their effects, and mixt them with their own hands.</p>
            <p n="17">17. Laſtly, if any ſtill think this way too troubleſome, and are unwilling to excuſe a little trouble for ſo many great convenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces both to themſelves and their whole Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, there remains yet another expedient for them, which they may make uſe of, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doing prejudice to thoſe, we are conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to enter into the courſe already propos'd: They may (if they pleaſe) have an <hi>Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of their own,</hi> and ſend their Bills to be made up by him as now they are; provided only, 1. That the time and manner of uſing it be not ſet down; nor 2. The name of the Patient. 3. That it be not ſent by the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, but by their own Servants. 4. That it be <hi>returned to the Phyſicians again with the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick</hi> it ſelf, to be fil'd up by them with the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients</hi> name added, or entred into a Book, as was ſaid before; and the Phyſick ſo made and provided by the <hi>Phyſicians</hi> order, to be fetch'd at their own houſes (as it is now at the <hi>Apothecaries Shops</hi>) or from thence ſent
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:59448:24"/>
home by their own Servants to the Patient.</p>
            <p>Now if we conſider how this way reſpects the <hi>Apothecaries,</hi> 'tis evidently a fair and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate courſe between them and the Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, not taking away, nor leſſening any of <hi>the priviledges</hi> and <hi>immunities</hi> granted to them by <hi>their Charter,</hi> or which they claim, and enjoy as <hi>Freemen of this City, or other Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Corporations. For it hinders not their making and ſelling of Phyſick to any that pleaſe to buy of them,</hi> which thing only belongs to their Trade: <hi>To viſit the Patient, feel his Pulſe, conſider his <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine, diſcourſe of the ſtate of the Diſeaſe, and preſcribe proper Remedies for it, is the buſineſs and care of the Phyſician.</hi> So that I dare preſume no <hi>Apothecary</hi> who is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to live on his own Trade without inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Profeſſion of another (and I doubt not but the greateſt number and ableſt men among them are ſuch) will think ill of it; but rather be pleaſed to ſee, that for the future all cauſes of jealouſie and ſuſpicion between <hi>Phyſicians</hi> and <hi>them,</hi> will for ever ceaſe, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts of both be preſerv'd, and the practice of <hi>Mountebanks</hi> and <hi>Quacks</hi> brought to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It will very much conduce to <hi>the profit
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:59448:25"/>
and advantage of the Apothecary:</hi> For now the people finding encouragement to addreſs themſelves to the <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> who before to decline the charge and expence of a Doctors advice, went only to <hi>the Mountebank,</hi> who made and <hi>gave all his</hi> Phyſick himſelf; It muſt needs come to paſs, that the <hi>Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> muſt provide and vend much greater quantities then they <hi>could before;</hi> And thus all that which went away to <hi>Quacks</hi> and other <hi>ignorant pretenders</hi> be brought into the hands of <hi>the induſtrious and careful Apothecary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. It will inſenſibly leſſen that exorbitant number of <hi>Apothecaries,</hi> which makes the Trade burdenſome to it ſelf, and ſcarce a competent ſubſiſtence for a man after he has ſpent a good ſum of money, and ſeven years or more in an Apprenticeſhip to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it. For as things are now, while the Maſters or their Servants are employed by the <hi>Phyſician</hi> to viſit his <hi>Patients,</hi> and carry Phyſick about, if an <hi>Apothecary</hi> have great buſineſs, he will be under a neceſſity of ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſeveral Apprentices, elſe he cannot per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form ſuch <hi>attendances abroad,</hi> and the buſineſs of the <hi>Shop</hi> too: And this has made ſo vaſt an encreaſe of the Trade within a few years, as
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:59448:25"/>
has rendred it but a mean way of livelyhood to a great many, and very dangerous to the ſick: Now as their number will by little and little grow leſs, ſo the Trade will become bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and they who are of it, both for skill and eſtate much more conſiderable.</p>
            <p>To come now and conſider how much more this way is for <hi>the common good and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of the people,</hi> and in general <hi>of all men.</hi> Firſt, it mightily abates <hi>the charge and expence of Phyſick:</hi> and this is the only reaſon, why ſo many perſons not <hi>of the poorer ſort only,</hi> but even ſome others of <hi>a better condition,</hi> daily put themſelves into the hands of <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tebanks</hi> and other ignorant perſons, to the great prejudice of <hi>the lives and health of men.</hi> Alſo many <hi>Poor of this City</hi> and other places (<hi>to the high diſhonour of Religion</hi>) periſh for want of neceſſary help; whilſt on the one hand <hi>they are terrified by the Phyſicians Fee,</hi> and on the other by <hi>the unconſcionable and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounded prices of Apothecaries.</hi> A courſe therefore is taken here, <hi>that all ſorts of people</hi> may apply themſelves to the <hi>Phyſician</hi> both for <hi>advice and Phyſick too,</hi> at moderate and reaſonable rates: Nor can it be thought the <hi>Phyſician</hi> will uſe a greater exceſs in the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:59448:26"/>
prices of his Phyſick than others have done, becauſe he does not depend upon the gains of the Phyſick he ſells to ſuch as come home to him, but (as he did before) upon the Fees which he receives from perſons of condition and ability, when he is ſent for out of his own houſe: For the trouble of ſelling his own Phyſick to ſuch as ſhall come to him, he takes upon him only to advance the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick intereſt, ſatisfie himſelf more in his own Profeſſion, ſerve <hi>Philoſophy,</hi> miniſter to the neceſſities of <hi>the Poor,</hi> conſult for the greater ſecurity of all, and to gratifie and oblige thoſe Patients whoſe more ample condition of life makes them able to pay ſuch Fees as have formerly been accuſtomed. But if any man ſhould ſell at as dear rates as others have before, yet is it to be conſider'd, that then <hi>nothing is paid for advice,</hi> which till now was <hi>a great and particular charge of it ſelf;</hi> and, beſide, Phyſick coſt as much as now 'tis ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to do. So that according to this Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, <hi>the charge of advice is wholly taken off</hi> to the great eaſe of the people, who will have at leaſt both <hi>Advice and Phyſick too, for the ſame rate which they before paid for Phyſick alone.</hi> But I dare not allow a ſuppoſition ſo
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:59448:26"/>
unreaſonable, and ſo much not only againſt the honour, but alſo againſt the intereſt of every Phyſician: for admit he ſhould make his Patients pay (as has been formerly done) for <hi>the formalities of a Bill,</hi> as for <hi>a Clyster, a Potion,</hi> or <hi>Julip,</hi> half a Crown or more, and not for <hi>the Ingredients,</hi> which (it may be) ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver coſt ſix pence: I ſay, if any ſhould take this courſe, it would quickly be his utter un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing; nor would any Patient make uſe of him another time: but eſpecially they would extreamly murmur to pay him thoſe Fees which otherwiſe he might juſtly expect, and upon which it is his intereſt chiefly to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend, and not upon the inconſiderable gain of the Phyſick he ſells, and chiefly when that ſlight gain ſhall make him ſo great a loſer; whereas by neglecting ſo poor and mean a profit he may have ſo handſome and gener<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous occaſions offer'd him of obliging his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients in ſuch a manner, as to get much more then he could have done by his Phyſick. And if I may take a conjecture from your ſelf, and ſome other Phyſicians my acquaintance, <hi>theſe of your Colledge</hi> are ſuch as would ſcorn from Patients ſo civil as to pay the ordinary Fees duly, to take more for their Phyſick then
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:59448:27"/>
what it barely coſt; nay, often would give it for nothing. And yet if they ſhould make ſome ſmall advantage, it might be allowed them for the money they lay out, for the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of themſelves and Servants to make up and diſpenſe the Phyſick, and ſtill it would coſt the people much leſs then before. And that all perſons would very frankly allow this, we have little reaſon to doubt, if we conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</p>
            <p n="2">2. The many advantages all men receive this way in the more ſpeedy, ſafe, and effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual cure of Diſeaſes, both in reſpect of the <hi>Phyſician, the Diſeaſe,</hi> and <hi>the Phyſick</hi> it ſelf. 1. The <hi>Phyſician</hi> adminiſtring his <hi>Phyſick</hi> himſelf will be under a neceſſity of taking greater care to have all he uſes very good, and moſt exactly prepared: for no man can now lay the fault upon the neglect or ignorance of an <hi>Apothecary.</hi> It reſts altogether upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and he becomes reſponſible for it: alſo by this means <hi>ſecret miſchief by poyſon,</hi> or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wayes is <hi>more eaſily prevented,</hi> when the publick knows where certainly to charge it then when it is diuided among ſeveral parties who transfer the fault from one to another. And ſince the Commonwealth muſt truſt
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:59448:27"/>
ſome body, they may as well truſt the <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician</hi> as <hi>the Apothecary:</hi> for though he write a Bill never ſo good and wholeſome; yet if it be not made as is preſcribed, any kinde of miſchief may follow: And, as far as the <hi>Apothecary</hi> or his Servant is now believ'd for making Phyſick according to preſcription, ſo far ought the <hi>Phyſician</hi> to be credited, for uſing only ſuch Phyſick as appears by his Bill fil'd up or entred; and this is no more then what is now allow'd to every <hi>Mountebank</hi> and <hi>Chymist,</hi> and what all ancient times have ſecurely put into the <hi>Phyſicians</hi> hand. 2. In reſpect of the Diſeaſe; it is now the general unhappineſs both of Patient and Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, that he is never almoſt ſent for, till things are brought to extremity, and all opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of curing near loſt: where, if the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe had been encountred in the firſt riſe of it with powerful and convenient Medicaments, the Patient had been again reſtor'd to <hi>Health,</hi> whoſe life it may be muſt now anſwer for the firſt omiſſion. 3. In reſpect of <hi>the Phyſick</hi> it ſelf; for the Diſeaſe thus met in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is often carried off with a little matter, which neglected, requires a long and charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able courſe. Again, the publick may be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:59448:28"/>
               <hi>That all Phyſick ſhall now be as good as the Apothecary can make it</hi> (elſe no Phyſician will buy it of him) <hi>or the Phyſician poſſibly contrive it, for his own honour and advantage.</hi> Thus in a ſhort time will <hi>the Shops of Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries be rid of all that unwholeſome traſh, that too many now abound with;</hi> and the poorer ſort of them who are forced to buy of others to ſet up as for the Countrey (which commonly is the refuſe of their Shops) will, as they juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſerve, be quite diſcourag'd. For though ſuch ſtuff might ſerve well enough to make up a Phyſicians Bill, who is not preſent to ſee what ingredients are uſed, yet they can never vend them to a Phyſician himſelf that comes to buy. Likewiſe <hi>the viſitations of Apothecaries Shops will be more frequently, care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and ſufficiently manag'd.</hi> And laſtly, <hi>Apothecaries</hi> will be more in their Shops, and not leave things to raw or negligent Servants as is too often done; for not being ſent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout by <hi>Phyſicians</hi> to their Patients, or with Phyſick; nor engag'd in any quacking practice of their own, they will have more leiſure and opportunity to attend making good Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, which is their proper buſineſs.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The charge of the people for Phyſick
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:59448:28"/>
will be much leſſen'd both as to the quantity and quality of it. For now many Phyſicians are forc'd to abandon my Lord <hi>Bacon's</hi> coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, who adviſes by no means to recede raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from any experimented Receipt or Form; becauſe this would bring them into the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of <hi>Apochecaries,</hi> and alſo diſcover their practice ſo, as the <hi>Apothecary</hi> might uſe it to their prejudice, as ſome have done: Not to mention how many are oblig'd to write a great deal more then is neceſſary, putting in things of great price and little effect to ſerve diſhonourable intereſts.</p>
            <p>I have heard ſome worthy Members of your Colledge wiſh alſo that a new <hi>Pharma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copoea</hi> were agreed upon: But it was quite of another Nature from that now in uſe: For although this be better than any other extant. Yet I know they well underſtand, it has many things that need <hi>Reformation:</hi> but that is a buſineſs that requires mature conſideration, and the preſent perplexity of affairs will not permit it; yet I think you are not unwilling the world ſhould know, you can take notice where it is defective, as well or better than a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of thoſe men, who would go about to diſgrace it with vain and impertinent clamors
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:59448:29"/>
taken out of <hi>Zwelfer</hi> and ſome other Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. It was wiſht that the Shops inſtead of the Medicines now commonly made, were furniſhed with Simples only. Of which, ſuch as are beſt and moſt effectually uſed with a little, or an eaſie preparation, as powdering, infuſing, boiling, and the like, ſhould be ſo kept as might longeſt preſerve their vertue and operation: and ſuch as are moſt opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive by a more curious way of preparing, <hi>as in Tinctures, Extracts, Eſſences, Elixirs, Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, Syrrups, Juyces, Robs, Conſerves, &amp;c.</hi> to be likewiſe in ſuch manner prepar'd, as may retain their vertues moſt, and likewiſe render them moſt durable. By which means, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the preſent expence of making them be more, yet conſidering their long durati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it will in effect be leſs then it is in the preſent <hi>Method.</hi> The Phyſician that comes to buy will be able to make a better judgement of their goodneſs, and may uſe them either either ſimple (which was the way of ancient times) or compound them as he ſees occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by which he will likewiſe come to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the many and great alterations that happen from mixtures of ſeveral things toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; he will alſo be more able to make them
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:59448:29"/>
guſtful and palateable; thus preſerving the <hi>Tone</hi> of <hi>the Stomach,</hi> which is ſo much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed by ordinary Phyſick, that in <hi>Chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Diſtempers</hi> it may be doubted whether it do not more hurt this way than it can do good another. Likewiſe in all compoſitions he will be ſure to have the vertues of every ingredient, which will ſcarce be found in the compounds of the Shops, as has well been obſerved by <hi>Zwelfer:</hi> yet he himſelf is not without his faults in the ſame kinde too, as my little experiments have informed me: In a word, <hi>Simple Medicines</hi> thus prepared and kept, are not ſo ſubject to corrupt by the uſual fermentations of mixt things, and ſo will be more effectual for the uſe of ſuch <hi>Phyſicians</hi> or <hi>Chirurgeons</hi> as have occaſion to carry them abroad with them (as <hi>Hippocrates</hi> has well noted;) or ſuch as are employed in the Service of <hi>His Majeſties</hi> Armies or Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vies.</p>
            <p>But, not to give you too much trouble with my long Letter, if we pleaſe to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſtrange and intricate variations of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, brought in partly by new Dyet, diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries of new places, the nature of particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Soils, and how theſe are mixt, combin'd,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:59448:30"/>
and complicated both with the old, and with one another; it will be the rather neceſſary to put ſomething of this nature in execution. I have often heard your ſelf, and ſeveral others of your ingenious Collegues diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe well and ſubſtantially on this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which makes me the more wonder at the late Writer of <hi>Medela Medicinae,</hi> who would, contrary to his own reaſon and conſcience, endeavour to perſwade the world, that this was a thing altogether unthought of, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by your <hi>Colledg of Phyſicians,</hi> but all thoſe who are commonly call'd <hi>Galeniſts:</hi> and yet he himſelf hath ſaid no one thing in that whole diſcourſe, concerning this matter, that can be pretended new, for which he has not cited the very Books, and words of ſome <hi>Galeniſt,</hi> or <hi>Methodiſt,</hi> as he calls them: And to me it ſeems the greateſt Argument in the world on your behalf, why his <hi>Majeſty</hi> and the <hi>Parliament</hi> ſhould ſhew you all manner of kindeneſs, that ſuch various and irregular changes daily appear in the <hi>Diſtempers</hi> of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Body: For if we allow <hi>Phyſick</hi> to be altogether <hi>Empirical</hi> (as he pretends) it muſt needs follow, that in ſuch things he ought to be eſteem'd moſt able and ſufficient, who is
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:59448:30"/>
furniſh'd with moſt and beſt Experiments, either from his own obſervation, and theſe are properly his; or by reading of Books, which afford him the experiments of all the reſt of the world, and can beſt conclude and argue from the Analogy, Correſpondence, and Harmony, they have to one another; ſo that a ſtudy'd Phyſician muſt in all conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of reaſon have far the advantage of any other. But 'tis alledg'd, You are too rigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roufly confin'd to the rules and methods of the Ancients, who had few or no experiments of this kinde; and likewiſe neglect that high and more potent way of <hi>Medicine,</hi> which <hi>the Chymiſts</hi> only know how to make uſe of. But 'tis evident, this is a very unkinde and unjuſt imputation; for though in the former age, when <hi>Chymiſtry</hi> firſt began to ſhow it ſelf in <hi>Europe, It was condemned for its novelty and dreaded as full of dangers;</hi> yet for any to affirm in theſe more illuminated times that <hi>Phyſicians</hi> ſo oblige themſelves to ancient Methods, as to deſpiſe or not conſider <hi>the differences and alterations of ſeveral times, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions, Dyets, Tempers, changes of Diſeaſes</hi> caus'd by theſe; The new and more exquiſite wayes of <hi>preparing Medicines:</hi> If he be a
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:59448:31"/>
man of learning and underſtanding, he muſt needs be thought to abuſe his own reaſon for ſome particular intereſt; ſince he brings ſo <hi>great a ſcandal</hi> not onely <hi>upon many worthy private perſons,</hi> but <hi>upon the freedom and inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity of the whole age;</hi> whoſe happineſs and honour it is to be unconfin'd, and diſdains <hi>the Pedantry</hi> of being enſlav'd to any name or ſect whatſoever: and when an Inquiſition of truth comes before them, can as little regard the names of <hi>Hippocrates</hi> and <hi>Galen,</hi> as of <hi>Paracelſus</hi> or <hi>Helmont:</hi> and as freely make uſe of any thing it findes good in theſe, as reject what is untrue or miſtaken in the other. And to meaſure the temper of the preſent time by that of the paſt, is ſo great an inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, that I will deſire no other inſtance to ſhew it, then out of <hi>that Book.</hi> For thoſe very men who were (as he ſayes) at firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by publick cenſure of <hi>the Colledge of</hi> Paris, <hi>Sir Theod. Mayern,</hi> and <hi>Quercetan,</hi> came by his own confeſſion, in after times to be held and reputed among <hi>the greateſt Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans of their Age:</hi> nay further, to ſee how lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle you deſpiſe <hi>Rational Chymiſtry;</hi> One of theſe very ſame men Sir <hi>Theod. Mayern,</hi> a great <hi>Chymist,</hi> and an <hi>excellent Phyſician,</hi> was one of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:59448:31"/>
the chief men of your Colledge in his time, and <hi>had a great ſhare in making the Pharma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copoea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Since then your ſelves look upon Rational Chymiſtry, as an excellent way of enquiry in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the natures of things, and manag'd with ſound <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Philoſophy,</hi> an excellent way alſo of preparing Medicines; ſince you are as much converſant in <hi>Chymical Authors</hi> as any others, and have as many and more aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, of learning and experience to judge of them (by which I am ſure you diſcern every day, as many vain and abſurd things in the beſt of them as any pretended Chymiſt can finde in <hi>the Pharmacopoea</hi>) ſince you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn no ſober perſon that loves this noble Art, but ſuch idle and vain men only, or, to ſay moſt ſoftly of them, ſuch <hi>melancholy Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators,</hi> who being wholly deſtitute of thoſe principles that ſhould make them able to judg with reaſon of their own experiments, and tranſported with the novelty and ſtrangeneſs of things they do not underſtand, boldly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture through the lives and blood of men, to make tryal of ſuch preparations, of which they (lighting on them by accident onely) neither underſtand the reaſon, nor the uſe;
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:59448:32"/>
ſince I ſay theſe things are ſo, you ought not to believe the wiſe men who govern the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of the Kingdom will ever conſent to take away ſo important a part of Phyſick out of the hands of ſo many ingenuous, learned, and inquiſitive men as your <hi>Colledge</hi> now conſiſts of, or ſo much diſcountenance an honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Profeſſion, and way of educating Youth in the Nation, and give it to ſuch as theſe; eſpecially ſince the very Philoſophical free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom you own and profeſs, has rais'd you ſo far above the poor and empty name of any Sect or party. If therefore your Committee for the <hi>materia medica</hi> be ſettled, as before was ſaid, it will more improve <hi>Rational Chymiſtry</hi> in all its parts, then any deſign theſe men can pretend to; Particularly in <hi>the Analyſis of Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getables,</hi> hitherto almoſt wholly untouch'd, which will I doubt not afford more noble as well as more amicable <hi>Medicins</hi> then <hi>Minerals.</hi> And in purſuit of that, if you would addreſs your ſelves to his <hi>Majeſty and His Honorable Council,</hi> and aſſure them you are ready to erect a <hi>publick Laboratory,</hi> for the uſe of <hi>his Majeſties</hi> Subjects, where all <hi>Chymical Medicines</hi> fit to be us'd ſhall be well and faithfully made up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>the Faith and Authority of the Colledge,</hi> and
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:59448:32"/>
expreſly appoint, that all <hi>Apothecaries</hi> whoſe Phyſick you ſhall think fit to buy, ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide all their Chymical things from thence; unleſs any Phyſician be ſatisfied to let him prepare them with his own hand, nor to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the uſe of any other <hi>Chymical Preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> to any of your own number, except he himſelf make and prepare them You have no reaſon to doubt but all wiſe men will think you are as able to perform, as thoſe, who if they could do but one hundreth part of what they ſo impudently promiſe, would be equal in fortune and eſtate to the <hi>greateſt Princes of the Nation.</hi> And if to all theſe real perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances you pleaſe to adde a little of outward ſhew and appearance, and aſſume at conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient times, and on publick occaſions, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent uſe of thoſe <hi>Ornaments of Habit,</hi> and other <hi>Inſignia,</hi> which the wiſdom of our An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors has thought fit, upon grave and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berate advice of <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities,</hi> to beſtow upon your Profeſſion; you will finde it was not done in vain, and that they well conſider'd, with theſe things the wiſe in all Ages have been wont to govern the frail and weak underſtanding of the vulgar. And that among thoſe who are no good Judges of
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:59448:33"/>
real worth, it is the only way to ſecure it, both from being affronted and contemned.</p>
            <p>I hope you will excuſe the much freedom I have us'd with you, the truth is, I have ſo great a zeal to ſee ſomething of this nature effected for publick good, that if your own particular intereſt joyn'd with it, will not prevail, I could deſire it may be thought ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſeable to provide for it by <hi>publick Authority:</hi> that ſo the burdenſome charge of Phyſick might be remov'd, and that noble Art rendred of more ample conſequence to the world, the profeſſors of it be ſo encouraged, as Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men may think it a worthy courſe of breed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for their Children, that Philoſophy may receive the benefit of its many excellent ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments, that a right underſtanding may be ever preſerv'd between <hi>Phyſicians</hi> and <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries,</hi> that every man in particular may finde greater comfort in the uſe of thoſe nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous Remedies, that <hi>Almighty God</hi> has pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided to ſuccour us in our afflictions: and laſt of all, that as our Nation has had the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of one of the beſt things that ever was diſcover'd in the Theory of Phyſick, <hi>The Bloods Circulation;</hi> ſo it may give an example to all
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:59448:33"/>
the world of the beſt, and ſoundeſt, and moſt rational way of <hi>Practice.</hi> With her Ladiſhips Service preſented to you, I remain,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir,</salute> 
               <signed>Your aſſured Friend and Servant.
T. M.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 13. <hi>line</hi> 23. <hi>read</hi> had, <hi>p.</hi> 20. <hi>l.</hi> 20. <hi>r.</hi> require. <hi>p.</hi> 21. <hi>l.</hi> ult. <hi>r.</hi> Friend. <hi>p.</hi> 22. <hi>l.</hi> 18. <hi>inſert</hi> Of. <hi>l.</hi> 20. <hi>dele</hi> that. <hi>p.</hi> 24. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>dele</hi> there. <hi>p.</hi> 29. <hi>l.</hi> 23. <hi>r.</hi> unactive. <hi>p.</hi> 34. <hi>l.</hi> 25. <hi>r.</hi> his. p. 36. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>r.</hi> worthy <hi>l.</hi> 8. <hi>r.</hi> unſeaſonably. <hi>p.</hi> 37. <hi>l. ult. r.</hi> muſt <hi>p.</hi> 38. <hi>l.</hi> 32. <hi>del.</hi> ſo. <hi>l.</hi> 23 <hi>r.</hi> what. <hi>p.</hi> 42. <hi>l.</hi> 23. <hi>r.</hi> for. <hi>p.</hi> 45. <hi>l.</hi> 12. <hi>r.</hi> lax. p. 60. in mar. l. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
